おじいちゃん
Grandpa!
Grandpa, what is this?
おじいちゃん これ何？
Where did you find this?
どこにあった？
In the fields.
そこの原っぱ
Come along.
そうか
I need to show you something.
教えてあげよう おいで
I’ve never told you about my past, have I?
おじいちゃんの若いころの話
まだしてなかったね
Josiah, you are still young now.
ヨシヤ お前はまだ子供だから
おじいちゃんのことを
そんなによく知らないが
But one day you’ll learn more about my life.
おじいちゃんは悪いことを
たくさんしたんだ
I did many bad things.
I used to worship false gods instead of Jehovah.
エホバではなく 偽りの
神々を崇拝していた
I even brought idols into the temple.
偶像を エホバの神殿に
持ち込むことさえしたんだ
I upset Jehovah very much.
それで エホバはとてもお怒りになった
私はエホバから厳しく
正されなければならなかった
And he disciplined me.
I begged Jehovah to forgive me.
許してくださいとエホバに
心からお願いした
Did he forgive you?
許してもらえたの？
そうだ エホバは本当に
憐れみ深い方だ！
Yes. His mercy is great!
Now, these are the words of Jehovah’s prophet Isaiah:
エホバの預言者イザヤの言葉がある
ここだ
“All who form carved images
「彫刻像を作る者は皆むなしく
“amount to nothing,
“and their cherished objects will be of no benefit.
彼らがあがめている物は
何の役にも立たない
“As their witnesses,
それらの像は何も見ず
“they see nothing
何も知らないので
and know nothing.”
証人にはなり得ない」
Now I want you to read
ヨシヤ お前にも読んで欲しいんだが
these words down here about a man who cuts down a tree.
木を切り倒した人の話だ
Let’s see what he does with it.
その木で何をするかな？
“Half of it he burns up in a fire;
「木の 半分を 火の中で… 燃やす
“with that half
“he roasts the meat that he e-e-eats,
それで 肉をあぶり
食べて… 満足する
“and he is s-s-satisfied.
“He also warms himself and says:
また 暖を 取って… こう言う
‘Ah! I am warm as I watch the fire.’”
『ああ 火を見ていたら… 温まった』」
Is that bad, Grandpa?
これって 良くないことなの？
No, my son.
いいや でも 残りの半分で
何をするか読んでごらん
But let’s see what he does with the other half.
“But the rest of it he makes into a god,
「残りの木で 彫刻像を作り
“into his c-c-carved image.
自分の神とする
“He bows down to it and worships it.
それに ひれ伏し 崇拝し
“He prays to it and says:
それに向かって 祈ってこう言う
‘Save me, for you are my god.’”
『救ってください
あなたは私の神です』」
That’s wrong!
これはだめ！
Why is it wrong, Josiah?
ヨシヤ どうしてだめだと思う？
Because it’s not Jehovah.
エホバじゃないもん ただの木だもん
It’s just a tree.
How does Jehovah feel about doing something like that?
これを見て エホバはどう思うかな？
Jehovah doesn’t want us to serve any other gods?
ほかの神に祈ったら エホバ嫌でしょ？
Right.
そうだね
Besides, can any other god listen to our prayers?
それに ほかの神は祈りを聞けるかな？
No! Only Jehovah.
聞けない！ 聞けるのはエホバだけ
そしてエホバは お前の祈りを
聞きたがっておられる
And Jehovah wants to hear your prayers, Josiah.
I always pray to him.
いつもエホバに祈ってる
Pray to him many times a day
1日に何度も祈りなさい
from your heart.
そうするなら お前がエホバを愛し
That shows you love him and want to be his friend.
友だちになりたいということを伝えられる
もし 間違ったことをしてしまったなら
If you make a mistake,
pray to Jehovah to forgive you.
許しを求めなさい
Even for a hundred mistakes?
100回間違えても？
Even for a hundred.
そうだ 100回でも
A thousand?
1000回でも？
Yes.
そうだよ
A thousand, thousand?
100万回でも？
Even that many—if you pray to Jehovah to forgive you
いくらでも…
お前がエホバの許しを求めて祈り
and you really keep trying to do what is right.
本当に正しいことを行おうと
努力し続けるなら…
ヨシヤ おじいちゃんは
ちょっと休憩だ
Josiah, your grandfather needs to rest.
Finish telling me the story.
つづきを教えてよ
Where was I?
どこからだっけ？
The angel.
天使がどうしたの？
Right.
そうだったね
Then Jehovah’s angel came down,
するとその時
エホバの天使がやってきて
シュー！
and whoosh!
he destroyed 185,000 of Sennacherib’s troops.
18万5000人もいたセナケリブの
軍隊を全部滅ぼしたんだ
Really?
すごいね
Yes!
そう！ それでヒゼキヤ王は
King Hezekiah learned
that we can always trust in Jehovah.
いつもエホバに頼ることの
大切さを学んだんだ
I like going to the temple with you.
ゼパニヤの話 楽しい
はは
Zephaniah!
ゼパニヤ！
You shouldn’t fill the boy’s head with such stories.
そういう話はしないでくれ
ヨシヤを神殿に連れて
行くよう 王から…
The king told me to take Josiah to the temple.
分かってる でも親父の言うこと
なんか聞くな ヨシヤは…
I know where you’re going, and I don’t care what my father told you.
The boy isn’t—
どうした？
Isn’t what?
父さん 寝てなくていいんですか？
Father, what are you doing out of bed?
ヨシヤは神殿に行きたがっている
Josiah wanted to go to the temple.
だから 私はゼパニヤに頼んだんだ
I had Zephaniah take him along ahead of me.
お前はそれを望まないかもしれないが
You may not want to join us,
but you will not prevent Josiah from going.
ヨシヤが神殿に行くのを
止めることはできない
As you wish.
どうぞご自由に
Enan, this is a good one.
エナン これでいいかな
Who should I be this time?
今日はだれになる？
I want to be King Solomon.
ぼくはソロモン
ぼくはダビデ王になりたいな
I was thinking I could be King David.
Quick!
急いでください！
Bring the boy!
マナセ王がヨシヤをお呼びです！
King Manasseh is asking for him!
ヨシヤはどこだ
Where is Josiah?
He’s on his way, my lord.
もうすぐ 来られます
Grandfather!
おじいちゃん！
Josiah,
ヨシヤ
よく来てくれた
my son.
Listen to me.
話したいことがある
Oh, Grandfather, you have to get better.
おじいちゃん 元気になって
ぼくを一人にしないで
I’m afraid of being alone.
お前は一人じゃない
You’re not alone.
Jehovah is with you,
エホバが一緒にいてくださる
and so is your cousin Zephaniah.
いとこのゼパニヤもいる
Jehovah is holy,
エホバは聖なる方で
and you must serve him
お前はエホバが望まれる仕方で
ただエホバだけに仕えなければならない
the way he wants us to
—and only that way.
分かるだろ
神殿で犠牲を捧げたり
The sacrifices and celebrations at the temple,
儀式を行ったりするのは
they help us be friends with Jehovah.
エホバと親しく 友のように
なるためのものだ
I tried to restore pure worship,
私は 清い崇拝を取り戻そうとしたが
but the people still sacrifice on the high places.
人々は今でも
高い場所で犠牲を捧げている
エホバの神殿
Jehovah’s temple—we’ve neglected it.
我々はそれを大切にしてこなかった
How happy the people were when they worshipped
正しい仕方でエホバを崇拝していた時は
Jehovah the right way!
みんな幸せだった
Jehovah’s temple and worship
エホバの神殿と崇拝は
再びそのようになるはずだ
can be like that again.
Look at me.
いいかい ヨシヤ
エホバにお仕えするんだ
Serve Jehovah, Josiah.
All other gods
ほかの神には何の力もない
are powerless.
I’m afraid of being alone.
ぼくを一人にしないで
You’re not alone.
お前は一人じゃない
Jehovah is with you.
エホバが一緒にいてくださる
How happy the people were
正しい仕方でエホバを崇拝していた時は
when they worshipped Jehovah the right way!
みんな幸せだった
エホバの神殿と崇拝は
Jehovah’s temple
and worship
再びそのようになるはずだ
can be like that again.
Josiah!
ヨシヤ！
お父さん 痛いよ！
Father, that hurts!
How is business?
商売はどうだ？
The Phoenician models are beautiful,
フェニキアのはきれいだから
おかげでよく売れてるわ ベン・マタン
and they’re selling briskly, Ben-Mattan.
Excellent! We’re making a bigger profit on them too.
いいことだ！ みんなが像を欲しがり
我々も豊かになる
They will bring blessings from Baal.
バアル様の祝福だ
今年も豊作にしてくださった
I can see the crops flourishing already.
Jehovah doesn’t like this.
エホバは像が嫌いだ
やめなさい！
Stop it!
We need the help of all the gods,
エホバだけじゃなく 全ての
神の助けが必要なんだ
not just Jehovah.
おじいちゃんはそんなこと言わなかった
That’s not what Grandfather taught me.
He said, “All other gods are powerless.”
ほかの神には何の力もない
Lower your voice.
静かにしなさい
Your grandfather knew Topheth better than anyone.
お前のおじいちゃんもトフェトで
犠牲を捧げていたんだ
You, my son, can become a mighty man with Jehovah’s help
ヨシヤ お前が強い男になるには
エホバとバアルの助けが必要だ
and Baal’s.
That’s not right;
そんなのうそだ…
that’s not right.
絶対違う
エホバを崇拝したいなら 神殿に
行きなさいって おじいちゃんは言った
If we’re going to worship Jehovah,
then we need to go to the temple.
Grandfather said that—
Never mind what your grandfather said!
もう忘れるんだ！
He’s been dead for two years.
死んでもう2年になるんだ
You are not to speak of him again. Understand?
おじいちゃんのことは
二度と言うな 分かったな
ゼパニヤ！
Zephaniah!
エナン ここから出よう
Enan, let’s get out of here.
Enan.
エナン
No!
だめ！
King Amon.
アモン王
Josiah.
ヨシヤ
Take it.
ヨシヤ 恥をかかせるな
Don’t make a scene.
All other gods are powerless!
ほかの神には何の力もない！
Agh! Let me go!
わー！ やめて！ いやだ！ 放して！
Not here!
言うことを聞け！
Not standing before Baal!
バアルの前にいるんだぞ！
Not—
ああっ！
あー
Well, if this year Baal gives us no rain,
今年バアルが雨を降らせて
くださらないとすれば
we will certainly know why.
その理由ははっきりしています
What the boy did today was blasphemous.
今日あの子がやったことは明らかに
冒とくです
What do you expect?
仕方ないだろ
あの子は私の父とずっと一緒にいたんだ
He spent all of his time with my father.
He must be punished!
あの子を罰するべきです！
Hold your tongue if you want to keep it!
調子に乗るんじゃない！
お前はバアルの祭司かもしれないが
この国の王は私だ！
You may be a priest of Baal, but do not forget who’s king here!
これは失礼いたしました
I most certainly will not.
Good.
いいだろう 下がれ！
Now go!
And take that with you.
それも持って行け
No.
いや
It will remain here for you to reflect upon, my lord the king.
これはあなたの責任ですから わが主よ
何だ！ やめろ！ うわー！
No! Argh!
Help! Help!
大変だ！ だれか！ 王が殺された！
Somebody has murdered the king!
ヨシヤ
Josiah, you’re not alone.
お前は一人じゃない
Jehovah is with you,
エホバが一緒にいてくださる
and so is your cousin Zephaniah.
いとこのゼパニヤもいる
王が栄えますように！
Long live the king!
Enan.
エナン
My lord
ヨシヤ王 わが主よ
is a king.
Zephaniah,
これはこれはエホバの預言者ゼパニヤ様
prophet of Jehovah, so good to see you too.
My king,
王よ お気持ち お察しいたします
I know you must feel so overwhelmed by all this.
お父様がおられなくなって
I will truly miss your father.
私も本当に寂しいです
He was a good, tolerant man
あの方はおおらかで
who allowed everyone to worship as they wished.
自由な礼拝をお許しくださいました
You know,
そしてご存じでしょうが
your father consulted with me regularly
お父様は大切なことは いつもこの私に
相談してくださっていました
on very important matters.
Josiah,
ヨシヤ
can we still shoot arrows sometimes?
また一緒に弓のけいこできる？
そうだね
Maybe.
では今日はこの辺で
We’ll leave you, my lord.
Again, my sincerest condolences for the loss of your father.
お父様のことは本当にお気の毒でした
わが主よ いつでも遠慮なく
お呼びください
I’m here
whenever you need me.
いいですね
OK. Let’s try again.
よし もう1回やろう
Keep your hand steady—like this.
しっかり腕を固定して… いい
Remember, don’t focus on the arrow; focus on the target.
矢を見るんじゃなくて
的をよく見るんだ
こんな感じ？
Like this?
そうだね
Good.
You’ve improved.
上達したね
Enan,
エナン 来ないと思ってたよ
I’d almost given up on you.
We’re almost done.
終わるところだ
Enan, let’s see who can hit center first.
エナン 勝負しようか
There’s no contest.
やだよ 勝てるわけないし
You have more time to practice.
I have to practice so that I can defeat Jehovah’s enemies.
練習しなきゃ エホバの敵を倒すために
The history of the kings teaches us
王たちの歴史から良いことと
悪いことについて多くを学べるんだ
much about good and bad.
When we carefully study their lives,
だからよく調べるならそのことが…
we learn that—
「…エホバを愛し 悪を憎め」ですよね
—we need to love Jehovah and hate what is bad.
分かってますよ でも ほとんどの
王は悪かったんでしょう？
Yes, we know.
But why does it matter?
Weren’t most kings bad anyway?
That’s true, some were.
確かにそうだね
They didn’t trust in Jehovah,
彼らはエホバを信頼しなかったし
近づこうともしなかった
and they didn’t draw close to him.
When the king does not search for Jehovah,
王がエホバを求めないなら
everyone suffers, even the good people.
みんなが苦しむことになる
だから 王たちの失敗から
学ぶべきなんだ
All the more reason to learn from their mistakes.
Do you understand what kind of influence a king has?
王の影響力は本当に大きいね
I think so.
そうですね
My grandfather was a great man—
祖父はとても立派でした
うちの親父に言わせると
マナセ王は残忍だったらしいよ
My father says that King Manasseh
may have been a little brutal,
but he was effective, and he was tolerant.
でも おおらかで 寛大で
He gave the people many freedoms.
民を自由にさせてたって
Enan, having freedom
エナン 自由には責任が伴うんだ
そして 責任というものは…
means having responsibility.
The responsibility—
また始まった
Here we go again.
The responsibility to choose who we will serve
私たちには どの神に仕えるかを
選ぶ責任がある
—Jehovah or other gods.
エホバかほかの神か
親父が言うには
My father says that after the Assyrians released Manasseh,
マナセがアッシリアから
釈放されてからというもの
worshipping only one god weakened him
エホバだけを崇拝するようになって
and he started ruling like an old woman.
その支配も腰抜けになったんだって
That’s not true.
違う 祖父はエホバだけが本当の
神だと学んだんだ 侮辱するな
My grandfather learned the hard way that Jehovah
is the only true God.
And you just insulted him.
親父は 自分の目で
見てきたことを言ってるんだ
My father simply sees the mistakes your grandfather made.
君のお父さんは 間違ってる
Your father should keep his views to himself.
How can you say that?
何言ってるんだ 君の父さんみたいに
Your father trusted him,
君もうちの親父を信頼したらいいよ
and you should too.
Besides, you can be loyal to Jehovah
そうすれば エホバにも
and to Baal, Malcam, or any other god at the same time.
バアルにも上手に従うことができるさ
You don’t honestly believe that?
ほんとにそう思ってるのか？
I do.
ああ もちろん
Your father keeps confusing people.
君の父さんはみんなを惑わしてる
だったら親に逆らえとでも言うのか？
So are you telling me I should disrespect him?
What about the proverb that says:
格言にこうあるぞ
「あなたを誕生させた
父親の言うことを聞け」
“Listen to your father who caused your birth”?
Enan, we must respect our parents.
もちろん親に敬意を払うべきだ
But all of us, including our parents,
でも 親も含めてみんなが
エホバから命をいただいている
owe our lives to Jehovah.
If we just go along with our parents
もし親と一緒にエホバの
憎まれることをするなら
in doing something Jehovah hates,
エホバより自分の親を高めて
いることになるんじゃないかな
aren’t we honoring them more than Jehovah?
He just makes me so mad!
本当に頭にくるよ！
“My grandfather was a great man, and you insult him.
「私の祖父は立派だった
侮辱するんじゃない
Zephaniah is a prophet; you must listen to him!”
預言者ゼパニヤの
言うことを聞くべきだ！」
預言者だと
Prophets come and go.
話にならん
He’s not even old enough to be a real prophet.
あいつはまだ若すぎる
What is he—25 at the most?
今いくつだ？ せいぜい25だ…
でもどうして 神々じゃなくて
エホバだけを崇拝すべきなの？
And why do we only need to worship Jehovah?
People worship lots of gods.
ヨシヤの前では言葉に気を付けるんだ
Be careful what you say around Josiah.
His over-righteous spirit may one day turn dangerous.
あいつの行き過ぎた正義感は危険だ
何をしでかすか分からん
You need to help him be more
あいつが物分かりの良い
人間になれるよう助けてやれ
balanced, reasonable.
どうやって！
How?
ゼパニヤは ヨシヤが
ダビデに似てるって
Zephaniah says he has a spirit like David.
はっはっはっ！
他人の妻を奪った 不忠実なダビデ
Unfaithful David,
who stole another man’s wife.
What is it?
どうした？
Talk to me.
言いたいことがあるのか
ヨシヤが正しいとしたら？
What if Josiah is right?
どういう意味だ？
Right about what?
神がただひとりだとしたら
What if there really is only one true God?
エナン
Son, Josiah doesn’t see the bigger picture.
ヨシヤの見方は狭すぎるんだ
あいつのじいさんは良かった
His-his grandfather did before he weakened.
腰抜けになる前は…
どうしたらいいの？
What can I do?
Talk to him.
あいつと話をしろ
Help him to be a good king
物分かりのいい王になれるよう
助けてやるんだ
—tolerant—
like Manasseh was.
マナセのようにな
Here’s what you can tell him.
こんなふうに言えばいい…
Josiah.
ヨシヤ
I just wanted—
ちょっと謝りたい
I wanted to apologize.
昨日は
あんな言い方をすべきじゃなかった
I shouldn’t have spoken to you like that yesterday.
It’s all right.
大丈夫 もう忘れたよ
I forgave you already.
ただ もう少し話したいことがあるんだ
I don’t want any problems between us.
It’s just,
要するに もし君が
間違っているとすれば…
what if you’re wrong?
そしてもし バアル崇拝が
必要だとすれば…
What if Baal worship is important?
Think about it.
考えてくれ バアルは
命をもたらす雨の神だ
Baal is the god of the life-giving rains,
and your father and grandfather sacrificed on the high places.
君のお父さんやおじいさんも
高い場所で犠牲をささげた
But what if Baal cuts off the rains
でももし 君がバアルを
崇拝しないために
because you don’t?
The crops would die, and the people would starve,
雨が降らないとすれば…
作物はだめになり 人々は飢えてしまう
and then they would revolt against you.
そうなったら 人々は
君に反抗するだろう
I know how you feel about Jehovah.
エホバに対する君の気持ちは分かる
でも 念のために
But isn’t it better to offer the other sacrifices too
別の神にも犠牲をささげた方が
良いんじゃないかな
—just in case?
Why would I worry about that when it’s only Jehovah
そんなこと心配しなくていい
天気をコントロールできるのは
エホバだけだ
who can control the weather,
not some false rain god?
Don’t you remember,
覚えてるだろう
King Solomon wrote: “All the streams”—
ソロモン王が書いたこと
「川は海に流れていく…」
I know.
ああ覚えてるよ
“All the streams flow into the sea, yet the sea is not full.
「川は 海に流れていく
しかし 海があふれることはない
“To the place from which the streams flow,
川は 始まりから また流れる」
there they return so as to flow again.”
That’s right,
エホバの設計どおりだ
just as Jehovah designed.
We studied that scroll together.
巻物 勉強したよね
だけど 巻物は書き変えられた
と言う人もいる
Well, some people say the scrolls have been altered.
Maybe the gods are trying to tell us that—
神々はそれを教えようと
してるんじゃないかな
Do you remember when we were little,
子供のころ
一緒に遊んだの覚えてる？
we would play in the fields?
Of course.
もちろん
君はいつもソロモン王を
やりたがってたね
You always wanted to be King Solomon.
確かにエホバはソロモンに
知恵と富を与えたけど
Jehovah gave Solomon wisdom and riches,
but do you also remember the end of the story?
最後にどうなったか覚えてるだろ？
大勢の妻たちは ソロモンの心を
ほかの神々に向けさせた
His wives inclined his heart to follow other gods.
彼の心はエホバに対してダビデように
ひたむきではなかった
His heart wasn’t complete with Jehovah like David’s was.
ぼくはソロモンと同じ失敗はしたくない
I don’t want to make that same mistake.
What are you drawing?
何描いてるの？
It’s the temple.
神殿だよ
My grandfather told me how beautiful the temple was
祖父は エホバを正しく崇拝した時
when people would worship Jehovah properly.
神殿は美しかったと言っていた
He said it could be that way again.
また必ずそうなる
I’ll tell you what I intend to do as king.
ぼくの計画を言っておくよ
父さんは分かってない！
You don’t understand!
Josiah plans to tear down all the high places!
ヨシヤは高い場所を取り壊すつもりだ！
Oh, I understand all right.
ああ よく分かってるよ
When his extremist ideas
あいつがその過激な考えを
行動に移してしまったら
become the law of the land,
there will no longer be any joy,
もうそこには喜びも 寛容さも
no tolerance, no freedom of worship
信仰の自由も無くなってしまう
—only narrow-minded rules
残るものといえば ただ狭量な支配と
and oppressed people.
圧政に苦しむ人々だけだ
Do you understand that?
お前そこ分かってるのか？
This is not a good sign.
これは良くない兆しだ
ただエホバだけに仕えなければならない
Jehovah is holy,
エホバは聖なる方で
お前はエホバが望まれる仕方で
and you must serve him the way he wants us to
ただエホバだけに仕えなければならない
—and only that way.
分かるだろ
お父さん 痛いよ！
ヨシヤ お前が強い男になるには
You, my son,
can become a mighty man
エホバとバアルの助けが必要だ
with Jehovah’s help
and Baal’s.
When the king does not search for Jehovah, everyone suffers,
王がエホバを求めないなら
みんなが苦しむことになる
even the good people.
What if you’re wrong?
もし君が間違えているとすれば…
Isn’t it better to offer the other sacrifices too
念のために 別の神にも犠牲を
ささげた方が良いんじゃないかな
—just in case?
ヨシヤ エホバにお仕えするんだ
Serve Jehovah,
エホバにお仕えするんだ
Josiah.
All other gods
ほかの神には
are powerless.
何の力もない
O Jehovah!
エホバよ！